DHRUV KOTECHA

+1 (551) 697 9486

http://linkedin.com/in/dhruv-kotecha | Tableau

dkotech1@stevens.edu

SUMMARY

Highly skilled data analyst with 3 years of experience in data collection, analysis, and visualization. Proficient in analytical skills with SQL, Python, Tableau, MS-Excel, and R-programming. A talented leader with excellent communication, management, and problem-solving skills with an ability to present findings to both technical and non-technical audiences

EDUCATION

Stevens Institute of Technology

Hoboken, New Jersey

• Master of Science : Information Systems | Concentration : Business Intelligence and Analytics

September 2021 - Present

• Relevant Coursework: Business Intelligence and Analytics, Applied Analytics, Big Data Analytics, Data Visualization and Application,

Database Management System, Social Network Analysis, Project Management

KJ Somaiya College of Engineering

Mumbai. India

• Bachelor of Technology June 2015 - June 2019

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Python, R, SQL, SAS, MS Excel (Pivot Tables, VLOOKUP, Formulae) **Programming Language:**

ETL & Analytics Skills Tableau, Power BI, Google Data Studio

Databases PostgreSQL, MySQL, Oracle, Microsoft SQL Server

Big Data Apache Hadoop, Spark, MapReduce, Hive

Libraries NumPy, Pandas, Plotly, Matplotlib, Scikit-Learn, XG-Boost, dplyr, Tidyverse, Lubridate, ggplot2, Rshiny, igraph **ML Algorithms** Linear & Logistic Regression, Naïve Bayes, Decision trees, Random Forest, KNN, Support Vector Machines

AWS S3, EC2, IAM, EBS, EFS, Lambda Tableau Training For Data Science Certifications

> Data Science and Machine Learning with R SQL Masterclass: SQL for Data Analytics

Power BI Essential Training

EXPERIENCE

Stevens Institute of Technology

Hoboken, New Jersey

Social Network Analysis Lecturer

September 2022 - Present

- Taught R-Programming and Python for Social Network Analysis to 100+ students in collaboration with Professor Dr Bei Yan
- Scheduled TA doubt session to solve student's coding queries and helped professor to deliver assignment activities problems
- Provided tutorials on network data analysis and assisting with assignments to provide technical recommendations on driven insights

Western Marine Traders

Mumbai, India

Data Analyst

January 2021 - August 2021

August 2018 - December 2020

- Performed in-depth analysis on 40 GB data using SQL to analyze customer datapoints and identify areas for improvement in business process
- Created 4 actionable dashboards using Tableau to derive insights for sales strategy and build roadmap decisions for revenue analysis to model cost reduction report from 4.8 hours to 15 minutes
- Collaborated with product managers for developing KPI's to determine product sales and identify opportunities that increased revenue by \$3.75M annually thereby reducing refund request to 32.74% and labor expenditure by 4.73%

Inventif Web

Mumbai, India

Data Analyst

- Executed data cleansing operation on a client's website and analyze metrics affecting website performance using SQL and Python
- Performed deep dive analysis and identified trends to reduce bounce rate, load time and traffic volume by 13.8% yearly using Python
- Worked with developers to enhance website's maintenance and fulfill business target, resulting in 17.89% increase in traffic throughout thereby reducing load time by 0.565 seconds

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Stevens Institute of Technology

Hoboken, New Jersev

Movie Recommendation System

August 2022 - December 2022

- Scraped movie ratings data, handled collaborative filtering using Spark to recommend top movies for user filtered by genres watched previously
- Visualized collaborative data, evaluated model using ALS and Regression Evaluator to validate results by comparing graphs in Databricks and AWS, with RSME -0.807, achieving an accuracy of 92.65%

Brain Stroke Prediction

January 2022 - May 2022

- Preprocessed data by eliminating missing values, centered data to avoid skewness and fixed misclassifications using Numpy and Pandas
- Visualized data using Matplotlib and Seaborn by analyzing factors (married, heart disease, age, smoking status) due to which brain stroke occurred
- Executed feature engineering, modeled data using Sklearn performed Logistic Regression (Accuracy 77.48%) and Decision Trees (Accuracy 84.43%)

Heart Disease Prediction

August 2021 - December 2021

- Analyzed Cleveland's dataset, performed statistical analysis, implemented t-test, chi-square test and developed hypothesis testing to identify factors responsible for heart disease
- Modeled data using logistic regression (AUC-ROC), achieved an accuracy of 86.9% and identified that people with smoking habits, irregular sleep patterns are more likely to get heart disease and validated this **predictive analysis** by **Tableau** visualization